Guide to the Jessie M. Bierman Papers circa 1890-1993
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Jessie M. Bierman Papers
circa 1890-1993
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 586
Bierman, Jessie M. (Jessie Marguerite), 1900-1996
4.25 linear feet
This collection contains the personal and professional papers of Dr. Jessie M. Bierman, a pioneer in the field of maternal and child health, from all stages of her life.
Biographical Note
Jessie M. Bierman was born on April 6, 1900, at Egan Slough near Kalispell, Montana, to Henry and Alice Bierman. She received her bachelor of arts from The University of Montana in 1921 and got a medical degree from Rush Medical College of the University of Chicago in 1926. She earned a master of public health at the Institute of Columbia University fifteen years later.
Dr. Bierman worked in private practice in San Francisco, California, from 1927 to 1936 and also served as an instructor in pediatrics at the University of California School of Medicine. In 1936, Bierman returned to Montana to work as Director of Maternal and Child Health in the Montana Department of Health. She started well-baby clinics in Montana that were a model for such programs across the country.
From 1938 to 1942, she worked with the Children’s Bureau in Washington, D.C., as assistant director of the Division of Health Sciences. She was chief of Maternal and Child Health of the California Department of Public Health from 1942 to 1947, during which she became a lecturer in pediatrics and a professor of maternal and child health at the University of California School of Medicine, a position she held until 1963. While at the University of California, she traveled to Germany as an expert in maternal and child health and served as a consultant on maternal and child health problems in India. Bierman also studied the children of Kauai, Hawaii, and published her findings in the book The Children of Kauai.
She was named professor emerita in 1963, but stayed on as the director of maternal and child health research until 1967. After that, she was the head of the maternal and child bureau for the World Health Organization in Geneva, Switzerland and was visiting professor of public health at the University of North Carolina.
Jessie Bierman was the recipient of the Martha May Eliot Award of the American Public Health Association and other distinguished awards. She was given an honorary doctorate by The University of Montana in 1967.
Bierman had a summer residence at Goose Bay on Flathead Lake. Bierman supported academics and research at The University of Montana’s Biological Station, endowing a distinguished professorship to support an internationally recognized ecologist to study and direct research at the Flathead Lake Biological Station. Bierman died in 1996.
This collection contains the personal and professional papers of Dr. Jessie Bierman, a pioneer in the field of child and maternal health, from all stages of her life. The collection contents begin with writings related to Bierman’s family history. The collection contains the memoirs of Jessie Bierman’s father, Henry, and her writings about him.
Items from her early days include a poetry scrapbook filled with correspondence and poems, her high school yearbooks, and diploma. Her student days at The University of Montana are represented by a scrapbook and diploma. Materials from her medical career in California include a set of house call diaries, 1931-1935. A scrapbook and related correspondence represent her years with the Montana Department of Health. Her positions in government and with international missions related to maternal and child health are reflected in correspondence and other writings. The collection contains the writings and publications Bierman completed while at the University of California and elsewhere, including the study she prepared regarding the children of Kauai, Hawaii.
The collection contains the numerous honors and awards Bierman received toward the end of her career. It also contains clippings about Bierman and other clippings and publications she collected on child and maternal health issues. The photographs in the collection are from all stages of Bierman’s life. Of particular interest are the family photographs, which include photographs of the Kalispell Meat Market that was owned and operated by Henry Bierman, and photographs of Henry and Alice Bierman.
The collection is divided into six series:
Series I: Henry Bierman, 0.25 linear feet, 1895-1985
Series II: Jessie Bierman, 1.5 linear feet, 1907-1986
Series III: Writings, 0.5 linear feet, 1924-1986
Series IV: Awards and Honors, 1.25 linear feet, 1918-1993
Series V: Clippings, 0.5 linear feet, 1935-1991
Series VI: Photographs, 0.25 linear feet, circa 1890-1980
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The bulk of the collection was donated by Jessie Bierman in 1987 and 1991. Another portion of the collection was a gift of the University of California-Berkeley, Bancroft Library, 2000.
The Bancroft Library at the University of California-Berkeley holds a collection of Jessie M. Bierman papers.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bierman, Alice--Photographs; Bierman, Henry--1860-1943--Biography; Bierman, Henry--1860-1943--Photographs
California--Bureau of Maternal and Child Health; Montana--State Dept. of Health; Kalispell Meat Market (Kalispell, Mont.)--Photographs; University of California School of Medicine, San Francisco--Faculty; University of Montana--Missoula--Students
Child health services--Government policy--Montana; Maternal health services--Government policy--Montana; Children--Health and hygiene; Children--Health and hygiene--Hawaii--Kauai; Maternal health services; Pediatrics; Women pediatricians--California--San Francisco--Diaries
Awards; Personal papers; Photographs; Poems; Scrapbooks
Women; Medicine and Health
Women pediatricians
- Henry Bierman, 1895-1985; Series I; 0.25 linear feet
  - Johann Heinrich Bierman’s descendents in America, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Henry Bierman’s memoirs and correspondence, 1895 and undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Henry and Alice Bierman Marriage Certificate, 1899 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Book accounts of Kalispell Meat Market-Henry Bierman, Proprietor, 1906-1926 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Henry Bierman certificates, 1939 and 1943 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Clippings re: Henry Bierman’s death, 1943 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Newspaper features about Henry Bierman, Montana history-general, 1949-1985 and undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, writings, clippings re: Montana: The Magazine of Western History articles about Henry Bierman, 1959-1961 and undated (Box-folder 1/8)
- Jessie Bierman, 1907-1986; Series II; 1.5 linear feet
  - Jessie Bierman grades, 1907-1928 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Flathead High School yearbooks, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Poetry Scrapbook, 1918 and undated (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Scrapbook-Autobiographical, 1920-1971 and undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Rush Medical College of The University of Chicago, Senior Class book, 1926 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - House call diaries, 1931-1933 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - House call diaries, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Scrapbook-Montana State Board of Health, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Montana State Board of Health, correspondence, clippings, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Children’s Bureau, 1937-1981 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1986 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Personal correspondence, 1932-1952 and undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - State of California Department of Health, 1942-1945 and undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - University of California-Jessie Bierman, faculty member, 1947-1984 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Notes about Geneva, India, Mediterranean, Soviet Union, undated (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Germany trip, notes and miscellaneous, 1949 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Germany trip with Unitarian Service Committee Public Health Planning Team, 1951 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Outgoing correspondence from trip to India, 1955 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Clippings and memorabilia from Soviet trip (1956), 1956 and undated (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Clippings and publications from Soviet Union, 1956-1969 and undated (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Trip to Soviet Union (1956) and other Soviet Union-related materials, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Trip via Asia, 1957 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Diploma: University of Chicago, Doctor of Medicine, 1927 (Box OS9)
  - Diploma: University of Montana, Bachelor of Arts, 1921 (Box OS9)
  - Diploma: Flathead County High School, 1918 (Box OS9)
  - Certificate: Montana Board of Medical Examiners, 1936 (Box OS9)
  - The American Board of Preventive Medicine and Public Health, 1950 (Box OS9)
  - Delta Omega, 1948 (Box OS9)
  - Art plates: Ajanta Paintings: Twenty Colour Plates, published in New Delhi, 1956 (Box OS10)
  - Student Scrapbook: The University of Montana, 1919-1921 (Box OS10)
- Writings, 1924-1986; Series III; 0.5 linear feet
  - Published papers-Kauai Pregnancy and Child Study, other papers about maternal and child health (some by Jessie Bierman), 1924-1970 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Publications by Jessie Bierman, 1924-1968 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Speeches/writings and radio broadcasts by Jessie Bierman, 1938-1986 and undated (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Writings by Jessie Bierman, 1958-1971 and undated (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Kauai Study, clippings, correspondence, 1960-1972 and undated (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Book The Children of Kauai by Jessie Bierman, Emmy E. Werner, and Fern E. French, 1971 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Martha May Eliot tributes, 1966-1978 and undated (Box-folder 4/7)
  - "Annotated Bibliography on Maternal Nutrition," by Jessie Bierman, with related news releases, 1970 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Publication, "Maternal Nutrition and the Course of Pregnancy" by Jessie Bierman, with related correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Curriculum Vitae drafts for Jessie Bierman, undated (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Notes, clippings and overhead transparencies for speeches, 1967-1969 and undated (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Miscellaneous writings and notes, undated (Box-folder 5/5)
- Awards and Honors, 1918-1993; Series IV; 1.25 linear feet
  - Certificates-honorary, etc. for Jessie Bierman, 1918-1964 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - University of Montana-awards, clippings, writings, 1960-1993 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Honorary Doctorate, The University of Montana, 1967 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - The Golden Grizzly Den, The University of Montana, certificate, 1971 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - American Public Health Association Certificate, 1977 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - University of Chicago Alumni Award, 1984 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Honors-miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, 1958-1984 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Plaque: "Healthy Mothers, Healthy Babies-The Montana Coalition Establishes the Jessie Bierman, MD, MPH, Lecture", 1990 (Box 8)
  - Plaque: American Public Health Association-Martha May Eliot Award, presented to Jessie Bierman, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Two academic hoods, one possibly Ph.D. hood, undated (Box 8)
  - Framed certificate: "The University of Chicago Alumni Association Professional Achievement Award", 1984 (Box OS10)
- Clippings, 1935-1991; Series V; 0.5 linear feet
  - Clippings about Jessie Bierman, 1934-1983 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Clippings about Jessie Bierman, 1937-1982 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Jessie M. Bierman Annual Lecture in Maternal and Child Health, programs, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Publications and clippings, health and medical-related, 1935-1978 and undated (Box-folder 6/6)
  - World Health Organization publications, 1957-1970 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Public health publications by others, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - University of North Carolina, 1971 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1978-1979 and undated (Box-folder 6/10)
  - University of Montana Biological Station, Flathead Lake, 1967-1986 and undated (Box-folder 6/11)
  - University of Montana Biological Station clippings, 1973-1991 and undated (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Poster: First Annual Jessie M. Bierman Lecture, 1963 (Box OS9)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1980; Series VI; 0.25 linear feet
  - Alice Bierman photographs, circa 1890-1948 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Henry Bierman and family photographs, circa 1902-1940s and undated (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Jessie Bierman photographs, 1918-1980 and undated (Box-folder 6/15)
  - California photographs, 1926-1979 and undated (Box-folder 6/16)
  - Germany photographs, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Foreign travel photographs, 1955-1956 and undated (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Soviet Union Trip-Seminar "The Equality of Women in the USSR," photographs, 1956 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Honorary degree photographs, 1966 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - [Bierman at home, Goose Bay, Flathead Lake] photographs, 1967 and undated (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Scenic photographs, undated (Box-folder 7/7)
  - [Jessie Bierman] examining a child, undated, [Jessie Bierman], undated; [Jessie Bierman] and unidentified children fishing, undated; [Henry Bierman], undated; Ida Shawers Bierman, portrait, 1887 (Box Negatives)